Finding Aid for Dept. of Physics (University of Michigan) records 1873-ongoing
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Undergraduate and Graduate Programs 1956-1991
  - Curriculum 1956-1991
    - Honors Program Report 1958 (Box 5)
    - Physics 120, Fall 1973 (Box 5)
    - Physics 240, Fall 1978 (Box 5)
  - Students 1974-1991
    The Students subseries (1974-1991) contains a small amount of information for and about Physics students.
    - Graduate Student Directory, Fall 1981 (Box 5)
    - Society of Physics Students, Information for Physics Majors 1974-1990 (Box 5)
    - Teaching Assistant Strike 1991 (Box 5)
    - Undergraduate Research Participation Grant Competition Results 1990 (Box 5)
- Research 1935-1987
  The Research series (1935-1987, 0.5 linear feet) is divided into five subseries: Directories, 1971, 1974; High Energy Physics, 1968, 1980-1987; Nuclear Research Project R-13, 1935-1978; Ultra Small Structures Research Office, 1983-1984; and Bolivian Air Shower Joint Experiment, 1966-1969.
  The Directories subseries contains research directories for 1971 and 1974. The High Energy Physics subseries contains correspondence regarding the Department of Energy contract, 1968 and 1980-1987. The Nuclear Research subseries, 1935-1978, contains correspondence, conference materials, meeting minutes, and reports on the financing, construction, maintenance, and use of the cyclotron. "Project R-13" was the name of the Rackham Trust Fund account which paid for construction of the cyclotron. The focus of this subseries is on medical uses for the cyclotron. The Ultra Small Structures Research Office subseries, 1983-1984, contains progress reports. The Bolivian Air Shower Joint Experiment, 1966-1969 subseries contains correspondence, journal entries, and obituaries concerning the mountain climbing dealth of Dr. Paul Barker while on research expedition.
  - Directories 1968 1971, 1974 (Box 5)
  - High Energy Physics 1968, 1980-1987 (Box 5)
  - Nuclear Research 1935-1978
    - Correspondence
      - Dr. Fred J. Hodges May 1935-April 1942 (Box 5)
      - H.M. Randall April 1935-October 1941 (2 Folders) (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous 1960-1978 (Box 5)
    - Conference July 18, 1940 (Box 5)
    - Meeting Minutes October 1939-May 1941 (Box 5)
    - Reports
      - Cancer Research 1936-1937 (Box 5)
      - Ad Hoc Review Committee of the University of Michigan Cyclotron Laboratory July 1974 (Box 5)
      - Neutron Therapy Proposal August 1975 (Box 5)
      - History of the Cyclotron Disposition December 1976 (Box 5)
      - Cyclotron Booklet, After 1963 (Box 5)
    - Finances
      - Trust Fund Ledger 1937-1938 (Box 5)
      - Project Budget Reports June-November 1975 (Box 5)
  - Ultra Small Structures Research Office July 1983-June 1984 (Box 5)
  - Bolivian Air Shower Joint Experiment, 1966-1969 (Box 5)
- Special Events and Awards 1945-1988
  The Awards and Special Events series (1945-1988, .4 linear feet) is divided into seven subseries: Dedications and Celebrations, 1979, 1988; Colloquia, 1984-1985; Lectures, 1978, 1990; Seminars, 1983-1987; Summer Symposia, 1953-1962; Workshops, 1990; and Awards, 1945, 1982-1987. Of particular note are the Summer Symposia, which were held on a different topic each year. The research proposal to the National Science Foundation for each symposia describes the topic.
  - Dedications and Celebrations 1979, 1988
    - David M. Dennison Building October 6, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Centennial Celebration Announcements 1988 (Box 6)
  - Colloquia 1984-1985
    - "Fusion Research at G.A. Technologies," Tihiro Ohkawa, Correspondence February 13, 1985 (Box 5)
    - "Warner-Lambert Lecture in Science," Mary K. Galliard, Correspondence October 31, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Lectures 1978, 1990
    - "The Prediction of Antimatter," P.A.M Dirac, Announcements April 17, 1978 (Box 5)
    - "The Freshman Year in the Sciences: How Important are Faculty Incentives," Homer A. Neal, Transcript April 6, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Seminars 1983-1987
    - Physical Science Seminar Schedules September 1983-April 1987 (Box 5)
  - Summer Symposia 1953-1962
    - Astrophysics; X-Ray Diffraction 1953 (Box 5)
    - Problem of Nuclear Structure 1954 (Box 5)
    - Problem of Nuclear Structure 1955 (Box 5)
    - Biophysics 1956 (Box 5)
    - Stellar Evolution and Abundance of the Elements 1957 (Box 5)
    - Teaching of High School Physics 1958 (Box 5)
    - Optical Pumping 1959 (Box 5)
    - Nuclear Structure 1961 (Box 5)
    - Nuclear Spectroscopy 1962 (Box 5)
  - Workshops 1990
    - Supernova Workshop March 15-17, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Awards 1945, 1982-1987
    - Faculty Award Nominations 1982-1987 (Box 5)
    - Naval Ordnance Development Award 1945 (Box 5)
- L3 Project 1974-2002
  The L3 Project series (1974-2002, 4 linear feet) concerns the University of Michigan's participation in a large, multi-institutional high-energy physics experiment called L3. Headed by Nobel Prize Laureate (and U-M alumnus) Samuel C.C. Ting of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) and based out of the European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN) laboratory, L3 has brought together physicists in more than 50 institutions to develop a large detector and conduct experiments to detect particles produced in the collision of electrons and positrons circulating in the LEP ring. Important results that have come out of L3 include the measurement of the lineshape of the Z0 resonance and achieving unprecedented precision measurements of various physical quantities. The University of Michigan has been a participant in the project since 1983, with its greatest involvement coming in the design and construction of the hadron calorimeter for the detector. Over 20 University of Michigan faculty, research staff, and students have participated in the project, including Department of Physics professors Lawrence W. Jones, Byron P. Roe, J. Keith Riles, and Michael Longo, and research scientists Tofigh Azemoon and Robert C. Ball. Ten Michigan physics doctoral students have published dissertations based on work done on L3.
  The L3 Project series is divided into four subseries: National Science Foundation (NSF), General L3 Administration and Michigan Participation, Hadron Calorimeter, and Audiovisual Materials.
  - National Science Foundation (Box 7)
    The NSF subseries (1973-2000, 1 linear foot) documents the U-M L3 team's interactions with their primary funding body. The subseries includes proposals, correspondence, and reports documenting the team's involvement in the project. This subseries gives a sense not only of the funding of Michigan participation, but also of its varying emphasis within the Department of Physics over time.
    - 1973-75 (Box 7)
    - 1976-77 (Box 7)
    - 1978-80 (Box 7)
    - 1981-82 (Box 7)
    - 1983 (Box 7)
    - 1984 (Box 7)
    - 1985 (Box 7)
    - Quarterly Reports, 1986-88 (Box 7)
    - 1986 (Box 7)
    - Review 1986, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1987 (Box 7)
    - 1988 (Box 7)
    - 1989 (Box 7)
    - 1990 (Box 7)
    - 1991 (Box 7)
    - 1992 (Box 7)
    - 1993 (Box 7)
    - 1994 (Box 7)
    - 1995 (Box 7)
    - 1996 (Box 7)
    - 1997 (Box 7)
    - 1998 (Box 7)
    - 1999 (Box 8)
    - 2000 (Box 8)
  - General L3 Administration and Michigan Participation
    The General L3 Administration and Michigan Participation subseries (1982-2002, 1 linear foot) lends insight into U-M staffing and involvement and the progress of the project as a whole. The subseries consists primarily of correspondence between the team members and other L3 participants and notes and reports documenting involvement in non-hadron calorimeter aspects of the project.
    - General Correspondence
      - 1983 (Box 8)
      - 1985 (Box 8)
      - 1986 (Box 8)
      - 1987 (Box 8)
      - 1988 (Box 8)
      - 1989 (Box 8)
      - 1990 (Box 8)
      - 1991 (Box 8)
      - 1992 (Box 8)
      - 1993 (Box 8)
      - 1994 (Box 8)
      - 1995 (Box 8)
      - 1996 (Box 8)
      - 1997 (Box 8)
    - Apollo Computer, 1984-88 (Box 8)
    - Computer
      - 1983-84 (Box 8)
      - 1985-87 (Box 8)
      - 1988 (Box 8)
    - Dissertation- In Search of the Standard Model Higgs Boson by Ross I. Berbeco, 2002 (Box 8)
    - Forward-Backward Muon Detector, 1991-92 (Box 8)
    - Graphics, 1983-87 (Box 8)
    - LEP3, 1983-84 (Box 8)
    - Lepto-Gamma 1991 (Box 8)
    - Letter of Intent 1982 (Box 8)
    - Longo, Michael, 1983-86 (Box 8)
    - Overseth, Oliver, 1982-85 (Box 8)
    - Parallel Processing Project, 1989-90 (Box 8)
    - Running Costs, 1991-96 (Box 8)
    - Software Meetings, 1984-88 (Box 8)
    - Trigger, 1984-85 (Box 8)
    - Vectorizing Geant, 1987-89 (Box 8)
  - Hadron Calorimeter
    The Hadron Calorimeter subseries (1.5 linear feet, 1983-1994) includes notes, correspondence, engineering drawings, and technical documents for all phases of the calorimeter design and construction.
    - General
      - 1984-86 (Box 9)
      - undated, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Barrel, 1986-88 (Box 9)
    - Chamber Construction, 1984-89 (Box 9)
    - EF Counter, 1988-90 (Box 9)
    - Electronics
      - 1984-85 (Box 9)
      - 1985-87, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1987-89 (Box 9)
    - End Caps 1988 (Box 9)
    - Engineering Drawings, 1985-87, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Glues 1987 (Box 9)
    - Instrumentation, 1983-88, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Layout 1986 (Box 9)
    - Mechanics, 1984-85 (Box 9)
    - Meetings
      - 1983 (Box 9)
      - 1986 (Box 9)
      - 1987, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - 1988, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Notes, 1986-89 (Box 10)
    - Papers, 1984-89 (Box 10)
    - Trigger Counters 1985 (Box 10)
    - Z Chambers 1994 (Box 10)
  - L3 Audiovisual Materials
    The Audiovisual Materials subseries (.5 linear feet) includes photographs, slides, and other materials related to the hadron calorimeter and the Michigan team. One videocassette is included titled, "LEP-3 Production."
    - Photographs
      - Hadron Calorimeter, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Michigan Group (Box 10)
      - Power Supply for the Neutrino Horn at Fermilab (Box 10)
      - NSF Michigan L3 Effort 1988 (photo album) (Box 10)
      - Unidentified Photographs (Box 10)
      - Unidentified Negatives (Box 10)
    - Unidentified Slides (Box 10)
    - Videocassette (Box 10)
      - LEP-3 Production (Box 10)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  A separate Audiovisual Series (1 linear foot, 1991-1997) was created with the addition of materials in 2006. This series contains audiocassettes, U-Matic videotapes and videocassettes. Many of the cassettes are unidentified and undated.
  - Audiocassettes (Box 16)
    - Myron Campbell April, 1994 (Box 16)
    - E.D. Courant undated (Box 16)
    - Larry Jones undated (Box 16)
    - Martin Luther King Day undated, 2 tapes (Box 16)
    - M. Perl April 11, 1991, 2 tapes (Box 16)
    - Lynn Rivers February 9, 1996, 2 tapes (Box 16)
    - Robert Savit May 6, 1997 (Box 16)
    - Gabriel Weinrich April 13, 1994 (Box 16)
    - Unidentified tape undated (Box 16)
  - U-Matic tapes
    - Experimental Areas Department undated (Box 16)
    - Fermilab's Lab C undated (Box 16)
    - Physics at Michigan undated (Box 16)
    - Unidentified, 1 tapes (Box 16)
  - Videocassettes
    - Hans Betha March 28, 1989 2 tapes (Box 16)
    - Norman Ramsey October 17, 1989 (Box 16)
    - Stockbridge on Target undated, 2 tapes (Box 16)
    - C.N. Yang November 13, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Ta-You Wu Symposium I May 3, 1991, 2 tapes (Box 16)
    - Unidentified, 17 tapes (Box 16)